Guide to the David S. Brown papers, 1915-1989 MS0001.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
David S. Brown papers
1915-1989
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Brown, David S. (David Springer)
MS0001.UA
78.5 Linear Feet
Collection include books, correspondence, articles, scrapbooks, notes, travelogues and a cap and gown of David S. Brown, who was Professor Emeritus of Management in the School of Government and business administration and program director for 31 years. The materials range in date from 1915-89.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated to the University Archives in three accessions by David S. Brown and Anne Elizon Brown in 1986, 1994, and 1997.
Biographical Note
David Springer Brown (1915-96) was a Professor Emeritus of Management in the School of Government and business administration at The George Washington University, where he was a faculty member and program director for 31 years. Dr. Brown was among those principally responsible for the creation of the Department of Public Administration at the university, functioning as coordinator, director, and chair. This included creating a masters degree program in association management, the first such in the country.
Dr. Brown was born in Maine in 1915, and earned his A.B. from the University of Maine and Ph.D. from Syracuse University. He served as a bomber pilot for the U.S. Navy in World War II, and saved his own life by jumping from a burning plane at 500 feet. His passion for flying continued throughout his life; he piloted 15 or 20 different kinds of aircraft. Prior to his coming to The George Washington University, Professor Brown served several private companies and also four federal agencies including the Department of Agriculture, the Civil Aeronautics Administration, the Air Coordinating Committee, and the Marshall Plan. In 1953, As executive secretary of the Mutual Secretary Program's Public Advisory Board, he helped inaugurate and undertake the first presidential level study of American Trade and Tariff Policy in American history.
He joined the faculty of GW in 1954 and specialized in the management of large organizations and bureaucracy. He was the author of several books, including Management Concepts and Practices, Management's Hidden Enemy - and What Can Be Done About It, Managing the Large Organization, and Federal Contributions to Management. In addition, he wrote several monographs and over 200 professional articles and book reviews. While at GW, he directed a number of programs. These included a senior executive program for the Veterans Administration, the Air Force Advanced Management Program, and a master's degree program in the management of national resources at the Industrial College of the Armed forces.
Dr. Brown appeared professionally as a speaker or trainer in a majority of the states and in several foreign countries. In 1958, he was Visiting American Professor at Chesters, a management training center in Glasgow, Scotland. He lectured for the U.S. Information Agency in Europe and Africa, directed many management training programs for both public and private sectors, and served as a management consultant. For several years he was President and later Chairman of the Board of Leadership Resources, Inc., a management training company.
Dr. Brown retired from GW in 1986, and died March 11, 1996.
An oral history done with Dr. Brown in 1989 can be found in MS0371, the Oral History Collection. The History Museum in Gelman Library was renamed the David S. Brown Memorabilia Room in November 2003 following a donation to the Library by his widow, Anne Elizon Brown. The collection was donated to the University Archives in three accessions by David S. Brown and Anne Elizon Brown in 1986, 1994, and 1997.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include books, correspondence, articles, scrapbooks, notes, travelogues and a cap and gown. They range in date from 1915-89, and were donated to the University Archives in four accessions by David S. Brown and Anne Elizon Brown in 1986, 1994, and 1997.
Collection Organization
Organized into 11 series: Books; Papers; Additional writings; Correspondence; Training materials used in classes; Faculty articles; Miscellaneous articles and manuscripts; Memorabilia; Personal papers; Professional writings; Scrapbooks.
Industrial management; United States; Europe; Scrapbooks; Public administration; Management; Washington (D.C.); Pakistan; Lovett, Evelyn; Lovett, Robert; George Washington University. School of Business and Public Management; Brown, Anne Elizon; Brown, David S. (David Springer); George Washington University; University of Maine; United States. Navy
- Books, 1961-1989; MS0001 Series 1; 2.5 Linear feet (Box 4, Box 3, Box 2, Box 1, Box 5)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains books authored by David S. Brown as well as books to which he contributed. They range from 1961 to 1989.
  - Managing the Modern City, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Banovetz, James M. (ed.). Managing the Modern City. Washington, D. C.: International City Management Association, 1971. David S. Brown wrote chapter six in this book. The chapter is entitled "Making Decisions", pp. 134-150.
  - Management Development and Training Handbook, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Taylor, Bernard and Lippitt, Gordon (eds.). Management Development and Training Handbook. Second Edition. London: McGraw-Hill Book Company (UK) Limited, 1983. Dr. Brown's contribution is entitled "Management Development In The Public Sector", pp. 72-80.
  - Improving Your Skills as a Supervisor, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Miller, Richard D., Richards, LLoyd W., and Miller, Dorothy A. Improving Your Skills as a Supervisor. Alexandria, Virginia: R.D. Management Associates, Inc., 1982. Dr. Brown wrote most of the material on motivation.
  - Cases In Public Management, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Golembiewski, Robert T. and White, Michael (eds.). Cases In Public Management. Chicago and New York: Rand McNally & Company, 1973. Dr. Brown was one of the contributors.
  - Cases In Public Management, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Golembiewski, Robert T. and White, Michael (eds.). Cases In Public Management. Chicago: Rand McNally College Publishing Company, 1980. Dr. Brown was one of the contributors.
  - Federal Contributions To Management, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Brown, David S. (ed.). Federal Contributions To Management. New York: Praeger Publishers, Inc., 1971. Dr. Brown wrote chapter one which is entitled " An Introduction And An Overview ", pp. 1-15.
  - Managing The Large Organization: Issues, Ideas, Precepts, Innovations, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Brown, David S. Managing The Large Organization: Issues,Ideas, Precepts, Innovations. Maryland: Lomond Publications, Inc., 1982.
  - The Federal Government and the Cities, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    The Federal Government and the Cities. A series of lectures delivered at The George Washington University 1961, Washington, D. C.: Dr. Brown wrote the chapter entitled "The Prospects For Action", pp. 63-72.
  - Cases In Public Management, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Golembiewski, Robert T. & White, Michael. Cases In Public Management. Third Edition. Rand Mcnally College Publishing Company, Chicago, 1976.
  - Ideas For Management, 04/1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Ideas For Management. Papers delivered at the 30th annual conference, held in Washington, D. C., April 1977. Library of congress catalog card number 55-2254. Dr. David S. Brown wrote a paper entitled "The Constructive Uses Of Conflict" pp. 223-229.
  - International Conference on the Future of Public Administration, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    International Conference on the Future of Public Administration, 1979. Dr. David S. Brown wrote a paper entitled "Bureaucratic Management in the Public Sector: Is Bureaucracy The Only Way?, pp. 201-247.
  - Some Observation On The Conduct of Technical Assistance In Public Administration, 07/05/1962 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Brown, David S. Some Observation On The Conduct of Technical Assistance In Public Administration: With Particular Reference To The Current Program In Pakistan. LAHORE: University of Southern California, July 5, 1962.
  - Concepts and Strategies of Public Administration Technical Assistance: 1945-1963, 07/15/1963 --08/23/1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Brown, David S. Concepts and Strategies of Public Administration Technical Assistance: 1945-1963. Prepared for presentation to the Comparative Administration Group, Boston University, July 15 to August 23, 1963.
  - Approaches to Development Politics, Administration and Change, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Montgomery, John D. and Siffin, William J. (eds.) Approaches to Development Politics, Administration and Change. New York and London: McGraw-Hill, Inc., 1966. Dr. David S. Brown wrote chapter No.7 entitled "Strategy and Tactics of Public Administration Technical Assistance: 1945-1963.
  - Executive Leadership, The Art of Successfully Managing Resources, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Grub, Phillip D. and Loeser, Norma M. (eds.) Executive Leadership, The Art of Successfully Managing Resources. Wayne, Pennsylvania: MDI Publications, 1969. Dr. David S. Brown wrote one of the papers in chapter four entitled "Importance Of Understanding Objectives", pp. 164-172.
  - Federal Public Policy, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Taylor, Theodore W. (ed.). Federal Public Policy. Maryland: Lomond Publications, Inc., 1984. Dr. David S. Brown wrote chapter No. 6 which is entitled "William Ashby Jump: Pioneer in Professional Public Administration", pp. 169-192.
  - Management Development: Senior Administrators, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Management Development: Senior Administrators. New York: United Nation, Department of Technical Cooperation for Development, 1987. Dr. Brown wrote paper entitled "Selection and Development of Senior Administrators" pp. 83-122.
  - A Report on the Air Force Advanced Management Program After Four Years, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Brown, David S. A Report on the Air Force Advanced Management Program After Four Years. Washington, D. C.: The George Washington University.
  - Inter-American Center Of Tax Administrators, 05/16/1976 --05/21/1976 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Inter-American Center Of Tax Administrators, Papers And Reports Of The Tenth General Assembly, El Salvador 16-21 May, 1976. PANAMA: Dr. Brown wrote a paper entitled "The Administrator and the Organization: Systems Thinking and Its Impact on The Administrator's Role", pp. 5-19.
  - Report Alcohol and Tobacco Tax Permissive Training Committee, 09/1960 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Report Alcohol and Tobacco Tax Permissive Training Committee, September 1960. U.S. Treasury Department, Internal Revenue Service, Document No. 5295(9-60). Dr. Brown was one of the committee members. He wrote exhibit No.1 entitled "The Role Of Training in management", pp. 1-7.
  - Selected Reading For Management In State Government Level "2", 01/1967 --03/1967 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Selected Reading For Management In State Government Level "2". Georgia: Training Division State Merit System of Personnel Administration. Dr. Brown wrote article No. 8, which is entitled "The High Cost of Hierarchy", pp. 8-1 to 8-8 and it is a reprint from the Civil Service Journal January - March 1967.
  - Course Note Collection (Economic Development Institute), 08/1980 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Course Note Collection (Economic Development Institute), World Bank. Reading in management, August 1980 Dr. Brown has two articles: 1) A Management By Objectives: Promise and Problems" Printed form "The Bureaucrat" Winter 1974. 2) "Modifying Bureaucratic Systems in the Developing World", a reprint.
  - The leader looks at Authority and Hierarchy, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Dr. David S. Brown The leader looks at Authority and Hierarchy. Washington, D.C.: Leadership Resources Inc., 1961. It was republished in republished in the Chinese language in a limited number for the In-Service Training Division of the Center for Public and Business Administration Education, Taiwan. It was entitled "The Leader Looks [of] Authority and Hierarchy".
  - A Trade and Tariff Policy in the National Interest, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Public Advisory Board for Mutual Security. A Trade and Tariff Policy in the National Interest. Washington: 1953
  - The Important New Role of Training, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    Brown, David S. The Important New Role of Training. New Delhi: The Indian Institute of Public Administration.
  - Management Concepts and Practices, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    Brown, David S. Management Concepts and Practices. Washington, DC: National Defense University, 1989.
  - Management Concepts and Practices: An Instruction Guide Prepared for Use With V. N4019, 1988, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Brown, David S. Management Concepts and Practices: An Instruction Guide Prepared for Use With V. N4019, 1988. Washington, DC: National Defense University, 1989.
  - Managing the Large Organization: Issues, Ideas, Precepts, Innovations, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Brown, David S. Managing the Large Organization: Issues, Ideas, Precepts, Innovations. Mt. Airy, Maryland: Lomond Publications, Inc., 1982.
  - Management?s Hidden Enemy-And What Can Be Done About It, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    Brown, David S. Management?s Hidden Enemy-And What Can Be Done About It. Mt. Airy, Maryland: Lomond Publications, Inc., 1987.
  - Federal Contributions to Management: Effects On the Public and Private Sectors, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Brown, David S., ed. Federal Contributions to Management: Effects On the Public and Private Sectors. New York: Praeger Publishers, Inc., 1971.
- Papers, 1953-1987; MS0001 Series 2; 3.5 Linear feet (Box 12, Box 10, Box 11, Box 8, Box 9, Box 6, Box 7)
  This series contains essays, cases, reports, and other professional writings of David S. Brown. They range from 1953 to 1987.
  - The Case of Reluctant Social Workers, undated (Box 6, Folder 1.1)
  - The Unhappy Clerk, undated (Box 6, Folder 1.2)
  - Reorganizing the Health Department, undated (Box 6, Folder 1.3)
  - The John and Mary Case, undated (Box 6, Folder 1.4)
  - Re-Shaping the Organization, undated (Box 6, Folder 1.5)
  - Poor Reports in the Investigations Division, undated (Box 6, Folder 1.6)
  - The Case of the Unused Capability, undated (Box 6, Folder 1.7)
  - Measures of Productivity -- A case study, undated (Box 6, Folder 1.8)
  - Public Relations or Production?, undated (Box 6, Folder 1.9)
  - The Case of the Section Officers, undated (Box 6, Folder 1.1)
  - Problem In Triberion, undated (Box 6, Folder 2.11)
  - Organizing the Beleeville Office, undated (Box 6, Folder 2.12)
  - O'Toole and the Review Auditors sic. Officers, undated (Box 6, Folder 2.13)
  - The Inspector Who Tried to Delegate, undated (Box 6, Folder 2.14)
  - The Case of Gordon Gregg, undated (Box 6, Folder 2.15)
  - The sic. Assistant Chief of Audit, undated (Box 6, Folder 2.16)
  - The Case of the Auditor in a Quandary, undated (Box 6, Folder 2.17)
  - The Case of the Missing Files, undated (Box 6, Folder 2.18)
  - Bill Tykes' Problem, undated (Box 6, Folder 2.19)
  - The Case of the Welfare Mothers, undated (Box 6, Folder 2.2)
  - A New Agency or a Reorganized Old One?, undated (Box 6, Folder 3.21)
  - Production Goals In Branch "A", undated (Box 6, Folder 3.22)
  - The Case of Bernard Bigelow, undated (Box 6, Folder 3.23)
  - The Case of the Displaced Clerk, undated (Box 6, Folder 3.24)
  - The Case of the Conflicting Instructions, undated (Box 6, Folder 3.25)
  - The Case of the Compensatory Time, undated (Box 6, Folder 3.26)
  - The Branch Chief and His Priorities, undated (Box 6, Folder 3.27)
  - The Case of Juan Caudillo, undated (Box 6, Folder 3.28)
  - The Case of the Tardy Girl, undated (Box 6, Folder 3.29)
  - The Case of Half-Way Bridge, undated (Box 6, Folder 3.3)
  - The Case of the Acting Chief, undated (Box 6, Folder 4.31)
  - The New Chief of Field Audit, undated (Box 6, Folder 4.32)
  - A Supervisor for Unit II, undated (Box 6, Folder 4.33)
  - The Importance of Radiation Engineers, undated (Box 6, Folder 4.34)
  - The Strange Case of Homer Flak, undated (Box 6, Folder 4.35)
  - The Sick Ella Ginsburg, undated (Box 6, Folder 4.36)
  - The Case of the New Work Standards, undated (Box 6, Folder 4.37)
  - The Case of Woman Who Wouldn't, undated (Box 6, Folder 4.38)
  - The Case of your Brother's Keeper, undated (Box 6, Folder 4.39)
  - The Barbara Smith Case, undated (Box 6, Folder 4.4)
  - The President Who DeLegated, undated (Box 6, Folder 5.41)
  - The Case of the Prospective RIF, undated (Box 6, Folder 5.42)
  - The Bill Ritt Case, undated (Box 6, Folder 5.43)
  - The Case of the Disappearing Cubicles, undated (Box 6, Folder 5.44)
  - The Gerald Gay Case, undated (Box 6, Folder 5.45)
  - The Boss and His Secretary, undated (Box 6, Folder 5.46)
  - Community Relations and McKay Barnes, undated (Box 6, Folder 5.47)
  - The Case of the Applicant with Long Hair, undated (Box 6, Folder 5.48)
  - The Case of the Training Award, undated (Box 6, Folder 5.49)
  - Delegation in the Energetics Division, undated (Box 6, Folder 5.5)
  - Personnel Practices in the Teenage Division, undated (Box 6, Folder 6.51)
  - The Case of the Unsigned First Baseman, undated (Box 6, Folder 6.52)
  - Presidential Dilemma, undated (Box 6, Folder 6.53)
  - "A Policeman's Lot", undated (Box 6, Folder 6.54)
  - The Westwind Story, undated (Box 6, Folder 6.55)
  - The Case of the $50 and $100 Bills, undated (Box 6, Folder 6.56)
  - The Case of the Loafing Employee, undated (Box 6, Folder 6.57)
  - The Case of the late Arrivers and Early Leavers, undated (Box 6, Folder 6.58)
  - The Case of George Gardlow, undated (Box 6, Folder 6.59)
  - A New Superintendent for Cloverleaf No.4, undated (Box 6, Folder 6.6)
  - The Superintendent at Hardrock Quarry, undated (Box 6, Folder 7.61)
  - Training The Boss, undated (Box 6, Folder 7.62)
  - The Case of the Troubled Supervisor, undated (Box 6, Folder 7.63)
  - Mary Topping, Teacher, undated (Box 6, Folder 7.64)
  - George Bronson, Principal, undated (Box 6, Folder 7.65)
  - The Proper Role of the Public Administration Advisor in Pakistan, undated (Box 6, Folder 7.66)
  - The Case of the Unused Capability, undated (Box 6, Folder 7.67)
  - Production Goals in "A" Division, undated (Box 6, Folder 7.68)
  - Setting Standards and Supervisory Work, undated (Box 6, Folder 7.69)
  - [Investigator] McDrew and the Auditor, undated (Box 6, Folder 7.7)
  - Harry and the Review Staff, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.71)
  - What Are Your Responsibilities?, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.72)
  - Some Problems for the Training Officer, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.73)
  - The Problem of Public Image, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.74)
  - A New Approach In Collection, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.75)
  - Some Assignment for the Training, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.76)
  - Trouble in the Recreation Department, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.77)
  - Small Group Assignments in Communication, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.78)
  - A New Approach in Collection, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.79)
  - What Are the Manager's Responsibilities?, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.8)
  - The Case of Unrung Cash Register, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.81)
  - The Case of the Unwilling Secretary, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.82)
  - The Case of the Reluctant Reviewers, undated (Box 6, Folder 8.83)
  - The Case of Mr. IN-Between, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.84)
  - The Crisis In Region Y, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.85)
  - Organizing The Bellville Office, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.86)
  - Miscellaneous Work for the Chief, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.87)
  - The Case of the Departed Clerk, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.88)
  - The Case of the Quarrelsome Revenue Officer, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.89)
  - Role Playing Demonstration, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.9)
  - EX Parte Wilkinson, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.91)
  - Dorsey V. The Regional Counsel, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.92)
  - The Case of the Ailing Auditor, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.93)
  - The Case of Unhappy Secretary, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.94)
  - The George Wright Case, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.95)
  - The Case of the Delegation which Didn't Work, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.96)
  - The Case of the Foreman-in-Training, undated (Box 6, Folder 9.97)
  - Public Policy and the Public official, undated (Box 6, Folder 10.98)
  - Case Studies in Committee Activity, undated (Box 6, Folder 10.99)
  - Case in legislative-Executive Relations, undated (Box 6, Folder 10.1)
  - The Woman Who Wouldn't and Other Cases, undated (Box 6, Folder 10.101)
  - Roadblock and Other Cases, undated (Box 6, Folder 10.102)
  - The Case of the Dirty Dishes and Other Cases, undated (Box 6, Folder 10.103)
  - The Public Good, undated (Box 6, Folder 10.104)
  - Case Studies in Public Administration, undated (Box 6, Folder 10.105)
  - Cases in Predictability, undated (Box 6, Folder 10.106)
  - Chapter I--The Nature of Public Administration (P.A.), undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    A Report on Public Administration Prepared By Dr. David S. Brown
  - Chapter II-P.A. At The George Washington University, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Chapter III--The Student Body, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Chapter IV--The Teaching Staff, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Chapter V--Market Potentials, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Chapter VI--International Programs, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Chapter VII--Research Activities, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Chapter VIII--Problem Areas; Recommendations, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Chapter IX--General, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Chapter X--Appendix, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Community Relations--And What We Can Do About Them., undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Other Writing Prepared by Dr. David S. Brown
  - Some New Tools of Management by David S. Brown and Kenneth M. Sowers, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Cases in Legislative--Executive Relations, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - The Role of Training in Management, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - What Do You Know About Your Superior? Your Associate? Your Subordinate? Your Self?, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - The Public Advisory Board and The Productivity Program, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Techniques for Teaching and Training, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Organization and Methods Conference 04/03/1957 Subject: The Role of Committees in Effective Management (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Suggestions for Filling out Standard Form 57 Application for Federal Employment, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Some New Tools of Management, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - The Nature of The American, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - An Emerging Theory of Management, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - What Management Needs To Understand To Successfully Communicate, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - A Manual For MSA: A Case Study, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - The Management Analyst: Who Is He And What Does He Do?, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - The Days In The Life Of A Budget Officer", undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Executive Agencies Of The Federal Government, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - The Civil Servant In The Federal Government, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - What To Do and What To See In The Marlboro Area Of Maine, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - The Role Of Training In Management, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Trade, Tariffs, And The National Interest: A Case Study in The Functioning Of A Public Advisory Board, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - A Trade and Tariff Policy in the National Interest: A Report to the President by the Public Advisory Board for Mutual Security, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - The Public Advisory Board as an Instrument of the Government, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 2)